Abraham: As we’ve had more time on
our hands during lockdown many more
of us have been using technology
to entertain ourselves, as well
as to continue our work remotely.
Children have been remote learning often
sharing devices with others in a family.
Mobile devices are commonly used by
everyone including those who have not
used technology before, such as the
elderly who now regularly 'facetime'
or 'chat' to family all over the world.
We are all using our mobile phones
more to order food, book appointments,
organise parcel deliveries, do our
banking, purchasing goods and book
medical tests and appointments.
This has opened us all
up to Phishing attacks.
Nicole: Covid19 has itself
helped to increase the level of
phishing attacks on individuals.
Any kind of change within the world,
produces an opportunity for criminals
to exploit people’s confusion.
As we search for more vaccine and
Covid19 testing information, vaccine
and test suppliers are becoming
targets of phishing attacks as are the
individuals who seek their services.
Bogus emails and SMS messages
about their services can affect
organisations and individuals alike.
This is also impacted by remote
working and the use of home networks.
Abraham: Phishing covers a range
of different social engineering
attacks which trick victims into
sharing sensitive information such
as passwords, usernames, and credit
card details for malicious reasons.
They can be random or more sophisticated
and targeted known as spear phishing.
This involves malicious emails being
sent to a well-researched victim.
Other forms of phishing like 'vishing'
or voice phishing and 'smishing' or
SMS phishing involve the use of mobile
phones and phone calls or SMS messaging.
Victims are contacted by what appears
to be trusted companies, banks or
organisations and told they have
to act immediately to organise
something or respond to something
by giving their private details.
Nicole: Most of us have had a message from
a parcel delivery company or some other
organisation asking us to click on a link.
Most of us know that this is bogus,
but individuals can be caught out
if they are expecting something to
be delivered or are too trusting!
A common example of vishing is when
an employee would be called by someone
posing as ‘IT Helpdesk’ asking them
to install something on their computer
which turns out to be malware.
A common example of smishing is a
text pretending to be ‘Royal Mail’
saying there is an import charge for
a fake parcel that requires payment.
Abraham: Other common threats come
from 'water holing' a computer attack
strategy where an attacker guesses or
observes which websites an individual
or organisation often uses, and
they then affect them with malware.
Identity theft and 'synthetic identities'
are becoming more commonplace with
the potential to affect us all.
These involve creating fabricated
credentials that are not
associated with the real person.